Louise Stevens Bryant Papers, 1885-1963
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Louise Stevens Bryant Papers
1885-1963
Bryant, Louise Stevens, 1885-1956
MS 24
14 boxes; 14 volumes (7 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Public health specialist; Editor; Publicist. Papers contain Bryant's diaries, notebooks, and professional reports concerning public health and social work issues; subject files; and correspondence from Havelock Ellis and others generated from Bryant's work arranging the U.S. publication of Ellis's Studies in the Psychology of Sex. Thre is also a typescript biography of Bryant written by her companion, Lura Beam, and excerpts from their correspondence.
Biographical Note
Public health specialist, editor, and publicist Louise Stevens Bryant (1885-1956) received a B.S. from Smith College in 1908 and a PhD in Medical Science from the University of Pennsylvania. She promoted dispensary development and edited a pioneer medical study and publicity program in the field of human fertility. She was associated at various times with the Russell Sage Foundation, the Girl Scouts of America, the Pennsylvania School for Social Service and Health, and the War Industries Board. She was the American representative of Havelock Ellis and wrote books and many articles on applied psychology and maternal health. She was the editor and publicist of the United Hospital Fund and National Committee on Maternal Health, New York City, from 1923 to 1937, and publicist for the American Association of University Women from 1938 to 1952. Her other interests included art, poetry, and animals. In 1909, she married Arthur Bryant, whom she divorced in 1912. Her longtime companion was Lura Beam.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Louise Stevens Bryant Papers consist of personal and professional material. They include a typescript of Bequest from a Life (privately printed), a biography of Bryant written by her companion, Lura Beam, and excerpts from correspondence to Beam from Bryant. The collection also contains Bryant's diaries, notebooks, and professional reports concerning public health and social work issues; subject files; and correspondence, including letters from Havelock Ellis and others generated from Bryant's work negotiating the U.S. publication of Ellis's Studies in the Psychology of Sex." There is related material about Louise Stevens Bryant in the Smith College Archives. The Lura Beam Papers are housed in the Schlesinger Library at Harvard University.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into four series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. PERSONAL ACTIVITIES
III. CORRESPONDENCE
IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
BOOKS ON SHELF
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Lura Beam donated the Louise Stevens Bryant Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1962. The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Search Terms
Birth control--United States--History--Sources; Children--Health and hygiene--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Eugenics--United States--History--Sources; Female friendship--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Maternal health services--United States--History--Sources; Public health--History--Sources; Social work administration--History--Sources; Women in the professions--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Beam, Lura Ella, 1887-; Bryant, Louise Stevens, 1885-1956; Ellis, Havelock, 1859-1939; Beam, Lura Ella, 1887-
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Marriage certificate and divorce papers, 1908-12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1867-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Smith College: photograph, booklet, and invitation, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - University of Pennsylvania: correspondence and booklets, 1912-14 (Box 1, Folder 4a)
  - Memorial gifts and keepsakes, 1930-56 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miriam Stevens (mother), 1908-36 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Illness: medical reports, charts, and insurance policy, 1917-26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Louise Stevens Bryant Fellowship, 1963-64 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Passport and related material, 1931-37 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Childhood: poem and correspondence, 1889-92 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Social Security: card and award, 1939-52 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Obituary, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Funeral materials, 1936-63 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memorials: receipts and programs, 1956-60 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Last Will & Testament, 1925-53 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Animal pictures, 1919-55 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Family history: notes and family tree, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence with Lura Beam, 1922-38 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bequest from a Life by Lura Beam
    - Typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Reviews and correspondence, 1960-64 (Box 1a, Folder 20)
    - Permissions, 1962 (Box 1a, Folder 21)
    - Williams & Wilkins Co., and Waverly Press, 1962-66 (Box 1a, Folder 22)
    - Distribution, 1963-66 (Box 1a, Folder 23)
    - Manuscripts and proofs, 1960-63 (Box 1a)
  - Personal memorabilia, [see also Oversize Material]
    - American Museum of National History, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Books: description by Lura Beam, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      [see Books on Shelf]
    - Contribution receipts, 1953-56 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Church, 1945-57 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Humorous pieces, 1910-28 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Myths of Plato, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Paintings and sculpture clippings, 1949-53 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Poetry, 1828-1953 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Clippings, 1945-54 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Prose clippings, 1929-56 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Vacations: photographs and postcards, 1923-60 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- SERIES II. PERSONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Clippings
    - Animals, 1935-56 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Birds, 1936-55 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Buildings, 1938-55 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Children, 1936-55 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Landscapes and flowers, 1938-56 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Men, 1937-56 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Negroes, 1936-56 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Obituaries, 1931-54 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Paintings, photography, and cartoons, 1937-56 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Poetry, 1921-34 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Reptiles and insects, 1948-55 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Sculpture, 1922-56 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - War, 1942-56 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Women, 1938-56 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Notebooks
    - "Psychology of Social Work, Principles and Techniques of Case Work, and Public Health and Hygiene," 1915-17 (Box 4)
    - Education course, 1907 (Box 4)
    - Physiology course, 1913-14 (Box 4)
  - Calendar: A Calendar of Good Thoughts to Companion Every Day, n.d.
    - Diaries, 1921-55, n.d. (Box 5)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Aronovici, Dr. Carol, 1941-44 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Ayres, Colonel Leonard (Dr. May Ayres, Mrs. Randolph Burgess), 1911-43 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Blank, Dr. Fritz, 1940-45 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Bryant, Arthur, 1904-14 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Bucky, Dr. Gustav, 1941-43 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Bucky, Frida Sarsen, 1941-42 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Carleton, Baldwin, 1939-56 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Carleton, Ernest, 1938-54 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Carleton, Dr. Spencer, 1933-54 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Churchill, Alfred Vance
    - Building a Collection, 1941-42 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Mid-western, 1944-51 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - German songs, 1941-43 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Churchill, Marie, 1953-55 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Cyon, Francoise Lafitte, 1935-54 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Dickinson, Dr. Robert L., 1928-50 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Ellis, Havelock, 1934-39 (Box 7, Folder 64-67)
  - F.A. Davis Co., 1934-35 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Emerson Books, 1935-46 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Ishill, Joseph, 1936-54 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - McFarlane, Ward, McFarlane Inc., 1935 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Random House: Bennett Cerf, 1934-39 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Virginia Quarterly Review, 1939-42 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-39 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Elwyn, Dr. Adolf, 1936-42 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Fay, Harriet, 1933-42 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Furse, Katherine Dame, 1939-52 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Guy, Gerda, 1945-56 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Hartman, Dr. Carol, 1935-54 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Hirschberg, Dr. Alexandre, 1942-53 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Hillyer, Marion, 1936-38 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Hine, Lewis & Sara, 1930-41 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Hodson, Mrs. Cora, 1939-56 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Kent, Elizabeth & Frederick, 1914-46 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Kerr, Rose, 1921-45 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Kopp, Dr. Marie, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Lord, Isabel Ely, 1940-54 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Nourse, Charlotte, Constance, and Mary, 1938-59 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Norton, Grace Fallow, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Patients - referrals to doctors, 1921-54 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Schaffner, Alice & Arthur, 1937-56 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Simonson, Ethel Bruce, 1923-55 (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Miscellaneous, 1914-56 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Re: Betsy Ross (dog), 1938-50 (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Letters of condolence, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 95)
- SERIES IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Notes
    - "The Precardial Arteries of Squalus Acanthias," 1908-11 (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - "Dante and a World Empire," 1908 (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - "Nietzche," n.d. (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - Philosophy II paper, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 99)
    - "Postural Patterns," 1936-37 (Box 9, Folder 100)
    - "Special Class for Defectives," 1908 (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - Mabel Ellsworth Todd
      - Correspondence, 1920-37 (Box 9, Folder 102)
      - Published writings, 1920-27 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - National Committee on Maternal Health, 1932-34, [see also Box 12] (Box 9, Folder 104)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets and publications, 1923-31 (Box 9)
  - Writings, [see also Books on Shelf]
    - Girl Scouts, 1921-23, [see also Box 11] (Box 9a, Folder 105)
    - Correction, 1915-63 (Box 9a, Folder 106)
    - School feeding, 1910-13, [see also Box 10, Box 12 and Books on Shelf] (Box 9a, Folder 107)
    - Miscellaneous, 1910-18 (Box 9a, Folder 108)
  - Nutritional Survey of Washington School Children, 1913-18 (Box 10)
  - Subjects
    - American Association of University Women
      - Correspondence, 1940-50 (Box 11, Folder 109)
      - Exhibitions, 1947-50 (Box 11, Folder 110)
    - Girl Scouts, [see also Box 9a] (Box 11, Folder 111)
    - Job hunting (Box 11, Folder 112)
    - U.S. Army (Box 11, Folder 113)
    - World food supply (Box 11, Folder 114)
    - World War I (Box 11, Folder 115)
    - Health and hygiene
      - Articles, topics for (Box 12, Folder 116)
      - Eyestrain in childhood (Box 12, Folder 117)
      - Maternal mortality (Box 12, Folder 118)
      - Malnutrition and incidence of disease among school children (Box 12, Folder 119)
      - Medical inspection in the public schools (Box 12, Folder 120)
      - Mothers' Assistance Fund, Pennsylvania (Box 12, Folder 121)
      - National Committee on Maternal Health, [see also Box 9] (Box 12, Folder 122)
      - Psychological Clinic, University of Pennsylvania (Box 12, Folder 123)
      - School feeding, [see also Box 9 and Box 10] (Box 12, Folder 124)
      - School feeding in Europe (Box 12, Folder 125)
      - Sterility (Box 12, Folder 126)
      - Work history (Box 12, Folder 127)
      - Records in social service (Box 13, Folder 128)
    - Social Work
      - Abortion (Box 13, Folder 129)
      - Central Bureau of Planning and Statistics (Box 13, Folder 130)
      - Committee on Dispensary Development (Box 13, Folder 131)
      - Hospital Social Service (Box 13, Folder 132)
      - Municipal Court of Philadelphia (Box 13, Folder 133)
      - Organization (Box 13, Folder 134)
      - Philadelphia Conference on Illegitimacy (Box 13, Folder 135)
      - Publication (Box 13, Folder 136)
      - Studies: reports and articles (Box 13, Folder 137)
      - Unstable diabolic blood pressure and feeblemindedness (Box 13, Folder 138)
      - Weekly reports (Box 13, Folder 139)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Girls' House of Refuge, Philadelphia: photograph album, 1908-09 (Box 14)
  - A Child's Primer of Natural History by Oliver Herford, 1899 (Box 15)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - By Louise Stevens Bryant
    - Better Doctoring - Less Dependency: A Study of the Relations Between Medical and Non-medical Agencies With Special Reference to Clinic and Family Services, 1927
    - Municipal Court of Philadelphia: Report, 1915
    - School Feeding: Its History and Practice at Home and Abroad, 1913
  - By others
    - Campward Ho!: A Manual for Girl Scout Camps by Girl Scouts, Inc., 1920
    - Clinics, Hospitals, and Health Centers by Michael M. Davis, 1927
    - Fourth International Congress on School Hygiene: Transactions: Vol. V: Papers, 1913
    - Human Sex and Anatomy by Robert Latou Dickinson, 1933
    - Human Sterility: Causation, Diagnosis and Treatment by Samuel Raynor Meaker, M.D., 1934
    - Scouting for Girls: Official Handbook of the Girl Scouts, Girl Scouts, Inc., 1920
    - Seventy Birth Control Clinics by Caroline Hadley Robinson, 1930
    - Songs For Our Darlings, edited by Uncle Willis, 1889
    - The Special Class For Backward Children by Lightner Witmer, 1911
    - Time of Ovulation in Women by Carl G. Hartman, 1936
    - The War With Germany: A Statistical Summary by Leonard P. Ayres, 1919